Let me show you a video.
>> This is a problem that many passengers
face every day on the trains, commuters
and long-distance travelers.
>> This is Jeremy Corbyn, former leader of
the Labour Party, sat on the floor of
the 11:00 a.m. train from London King's
Cross to Newcastle on the 11th of
August, 2016. The furore which followed
the release of this clip consumed the
British media for more than a week.
>> A row brewing over claims made by Jeremy
Corbyn that a train service he used
between London and Newcastle was ramped.
>> It was a whole thing.
>> I was planning or joking here that the
coverage was a bit like a true crime
documentary. Then I discovered this
actual AI-generated true crime style
podcast about the incident.
>> Buckle up because we're diving deep into
Traingate.
>> Never before have I felt like the
machines are coming for my job so
specifically.
>> Likely a big part of the reason that
this incident touched a nerve with
Branson and then went on to capture the
attention of news audiences is that
overcrowding on British trains is a big
issue.
>> Overcrowding on peak times is less than
it was. There is also, though,
overcrowding on long-distance services,
and that's why that's one of the reasons
we need to change how the fares work.
>> A study published last year found that
on a typical day, passengers were forced
to stand on more than a third of
services during peak hours. In London,
more than a quarter of all passengers
during peak times traveled standing up.
So persistent is this issue and so
passionate do people feel about it that
train overcrowding in the United Kingdom
has its own dedicated Wikipedia page.
>> Overcrowding on trains is bad enough in
and of itself, but the anger which
passengers often feel about overcrowding
is inseparable from the anger that
people feel about prices.
>> People feel pissed off that not only are
they paying through the nose for a
ticket, there's also a reasonable chance
that they might not even get a seat. And
standing on the train, particularly
trains which aren't designed for
standing, it really sucks. And yet, the
inconvenient truth for British rail
passengers is that your ticket isn't
expensive in spite of the fact that
you're standing, [music]
it's kind of expensive because you're
standing. It all comes right back to
very basic principles of supply and
demand. Train travel is really, really
popular in Britain. Of course, the fact
that train fares are set by government
here in the UK means the government
could opt to keep prices low anyway.
High fares and complicated ticketing
then are the current method which the
industry uses to incentivize people to
travel at less busy times. If you wanted
to be able to [music] tackle both
overcrowding and ticket price inflation,
then you would have to increase the
number of seats which are [music]
available to buy. And if the government
currently seems a little [music] bit
hesitant about the prospect of doing
that, it's because adding more seats is
actually a bunch more complicated than
it might first sound.